<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?rfc toc="yes" comments="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> <!--Requirements-->
<!ENTITY rfc3394 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3394.xml'> <!--Key wrap-->
<!ENTITY rfc3629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4634 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4634.xml'> <!--HMAC-SHA-->
<!ENTITY rfc5077 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5077.xml'> <!--Session tickets-->
<!ENTITY rfc5116 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5116.xml'> <!--AEAD-->
<!ENTITY rfc5705 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5705.xml'> <!--Key export-->
<!ENTITY rfc5746 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5746.xml'> <!--Key export-->
<!ENTITY rfc5905 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml'> <!--NTP-->
<!ENTITY rfc6347 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml'> <!--DTLS-->
<!ENTITY rfc7301 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7301.xml'> <!--ALPN-->
<!ENTITY rfc7384 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7384.xml'> <!--Security considerations-->
<!ENTITY rfc7507 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7507.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7465 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7465.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7627 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7627.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7821 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7821.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7822 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7822.xml'>
]>
<rfc docName="draft-dfranke-nts-00"
     category="std"
     xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title>
      Network Time Security
    </title>
    <author fullname="Daniel Fox Franke" initials="D" surname="Franke">
      <organization abbrev="Akamai">Akamai Technologies, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>150 Broadway</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>02142</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dafranke@akamai.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.dfranke.us</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        This memo specifies Network Time Security (NTS), a mechanism
        for using <xref target="RFC6347">Datagram Transport Layer
        Security</xref> (DTLS) to provide cryptographic security for
        network time synchronization. A complete specification is
        provided for applying NTS to the <xref target="RFC5905">Network
        Time Protocol</xref>. Certain sections, however, are not
        inherently NTP-specific and include guidance on how future
        work may apply them to other time synchronization protocols
        such as the <xref target="IEC.61588_2009">Precision Time
        Protocol</xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The Network Time Protocol includes many different operating
        modes to support various network topologies. In addition to
        its best-known and most-widely-used client/server mode, it
        also includes modes for synchronization between symmetric
        peers, a broadcast mode, and a control mode for server
        monitoring and administration. These various modes have
        differing and contradictory requirements for security and
        performance. Symmetric and control modes demand mutual
        authentication and mutual replay protection, and for certain
        message types control mode may require confidentiality as well
        as authentication. Client/server mode places more stringent
        requirements on resource utilization than other modes, because
        servers may have  vast number of clients and be unable to afford
        to maintain per-client state. However, client/server mode also
        has more relaxed security needs, because only the client requires
        replay protection: it is harmless for servers to process
        replayed packets.
      </t>
      <t>
        The security demands of symmetric and control modes are in
        conflict with the resource-utilization demands of client/server
        mode any scheme which provides replay protection inherently
        involves maintaining some state to keep track of what messages
        have already been seen. Since therefore no single approach can
        simultaneously satisfy the needs of all modes, Network Time
        Security consists of not one protocol but a suite of them:
        <list>
          <t>
            The &quot;NTS-encapsulated NTPv4&quot; protocol is little
            more than &quot;NTP over DTLS&quot;: the two endpoints
            perform a DTLS handshake and then exchange NTP packets
            encapsulated as DTLS Application Data. It is suitable for
            symmetric and control modes, and is also secure for
            client/server mode but relatively wasteful of server
            resources.
          </t>
          <t>
            The &quot;NTS Key Establishment&quot; protocol (NTS-KE) uses
            DTLS to establish key material and negotiate some additional
            protocol options, but then quickly closes the DTLS channel
            and does not use it for the exchange of time packets. NTS-KE
            is designed to be extensible, and might be extended to
            support key establishment for other protocols such as PTP.
          </t>
          <t>
            The "NTS extensions for NTPv4" are a collection of NTP
            extension fields for cryptographically securing NTPv4 using
            key material previously negotiated using NTS-KE. They are
            suitable for securing client/server mode because the server
            can implement them without retaining per-client state, but
            on the other hand are suitable *only* for client/server mode
            because only the client, and not the server, is protected
            from replay.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>
        The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
        &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL
        NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
        &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
        &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="DTLS profile for Network Time Security" anchor="dtls-profile">
      <t>
        Since securing time protocols is (as of 2016) a novel
        application of DTLS, no backward-compatibility concerns exist
        to justify using obsolete, insecure, or otherwise broken DTLS
        features or versions. We therefore put forward the following
        requirements and guidelines, roughly representing 2016's best
        practices.
      </t>
      <t>
        Implementations MUST NOT negotiate DTLS versions earlier than
        1.2.
      </t>
      <t>
        Implementations willing to negotiate more than one possible
        version of DTLS SHOULD NOT respond to handshake failures by
        retrying with a downgraded protocol version. If they do, they
        MUST implement <xref target="RFC7507"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        DTLS clients MUST NOT offer, and DTLS servers MUST not select,
        RC4 cipher suites. <xref target="RFC7465"/>
      </t>
      <t>
        DTLS clients SHOULD offer, and DTLS servers SHOULD accept, the
        <xref target="RFC5746">TLS Renegotiation Indication
        Extension</xref>. Regardless, they MUST NOT initiate or permit
        insecure renegotiation. (*)
      </t>
      <t>
        DTLS clients SHOULD offer, and DTLS servers SHOULD accept, the
        <xref target="RFC7627">TLS Session Hash and Extended Master
        Secret Extension</xref>. (*)
      </t>
      <t>
        Use of the <xref target="RFC7301">Application-Layer Protocol
        Negotation Extension</xref> is integral to NTS and support for
        it is REQUIRED for interoperability.
      </t>
      <t>
        (*): Note that DTLS 1.3 or beyond may render the indicated
        recommendations inapplicable.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Transport mechanisms for DTLS records"
             anchor="transport-mechanisms">
      <t>
        This section specifies two mechanisms, one REQUIRED and one
        OPTIONAL, for exchanging NTS-related DTLS records. It is
        intended that the choice of transport mechanism be orthogonal
        to any concerns at the application layer: DTLS records SHOULD
        receive identical disposition regardless of which mechanism
        they arrive by.
      </t>
      <section title="Transport via NTS port">
        <t>
          In this transport mechanism, DTLS records, formatted
          according to <xref target="RFC6347">RFC 6347</xref> or a
          subsequent revision thereof, are exchanged directly on UDP
          port [[TBD]], with one DTLS record per UDP packet and no
          additional layer of encapsulation between the UDP header
          and the DTLS record.

          Servers which implement NTS MUST support this mechanism.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Transport via NTP extension field">
        <t>
          In this transport mechanism, DTLS records are exchanged
          within extension fields of specially-formed NTP packets,
          which are themselves exchanged via the usual NTP service
          port (123/udp). NTP packets conveying DTLS records SHALL be
          formatted as in <xref target="dtls-packet-layout"/>.  They
          MUST NOT contain any other extensions or a legacy MAC field.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="dtls-packet-layout"
                title="Format of NTP packets conveying DTLS records">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                     NTP Header (48 octets)                    .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Extension Type         |       Extension Length      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                     DTLS Record (variable)                    .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               |                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               +
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                    Padding (1-24 octets)                      .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Within the NTP header,
          <list>
            <t>The Leap Indicator field SHALL be set to 3 (unsynchronized).</t>
            <t>The Version Number field SHALL be set to 4.</t>
            <t>
              DTLS clients SHALL set the Mode field to 3, and DTLS
              servers SHALL set the Mode field to 4, even if the DTLS
              record is being used (in the full-encapsulation
              protocol) to protect some NTP mode other than
              client/server.
            </t>
            <t>The Stratum field SHALL be set to 0 (unspecified or invalid).</t>
            <t>
              The Reference ID field (conveying a kiss code) SHALL be
              set to &quot;DTLS&quot;
            </t>
            <t>
              DTLS servers SHALL set the origin timestamp field from
              the transmit timestamp field of the packet most recently
              received from the client.
            </t>
            <t>
              All other header fields MUST be ignored by the receiver,
              and MAY contain arbitrary or bogus values.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Extension Type field SHALL be set to [[TBD]]. The
          Extension Length field SHALL be computed and set as per
          <xref target="RFC7822">RFC 7822</xref>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The DTLS Record field SHALL contain a DTLS Record formatted
          as per <xref target="RFC6347">RFC 6347</xref> or a subsequent
          revision thereof.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Padding field SHALL contain between 1 and 24 octets of
          padding, with every octet set to the number of padding
          octets included, e.g., &quot;01&quot;, &quot;02 02&quot;, or
          &quot;03 03 03&quot;. The number of padding bytes should be
          chosen in order to comply with the <xref
          target="RFC7822">RFC 7822</xref> requirement that (in the
          absence of a legacy MAC) extensions have a total length in
          octets (including the four octets for the type and length
          fields) which is at least 28 and divisible by
          4. Furthermore, since future revisions of DTLS may employ
          record formats that are not self-delimiting, at least one
          octet of padding MUST be included so that receivers can
          unambiguously determine where the DTLS record ends and the
          padding begins. If the length of the DTLS record is already
          at least 24 and a multiple of 4, then the correct amount of
          padding to include is 4 octets.
        </t>
        <t>
          The NTP header values specified above are selected such that
          NTP implementations which do not understand NTS will
          interpret the packet as an innocuous no-op and not attempt
          to use it for time synchronization. To NTS-aware
          implementations, however, these packets are best understood
          as not being NTP packets at all, but simply a means of
          &quot;smuggling&quot; arbitrary DTLS records across port
          123/udp. Indeed, these records need not be pertinent to NTP
          at all — for example, they could be NTS-KE messages
          eventually intended for securing PTP traffic.
        </t>
        <t>
          This transport mechanism is intended for use as a fallback
          in situations where firewalls or other middleboxes are
          preventing communication on the NTS port. Support for it is
          OPTIONAL.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="The NTS-encapsulated NTPv4 protocol">
      <t>
        The NTS-encapsulated NTPv4 protocol is carried out by
        exchanging DTLS records using one of the two transports
        specified in <xref target="transport-mechanisms"/>. The two
        endpoints carry out a DTLS handshake in conformance with <xref
        target="dtls-profile"/>, with the client offering (via an <xref
        target="RFC7301">ALPN</xref> extension), and the server
        accepting, an application-layer protocol of &quot;ntp/4&quot;.
        Once the handshake is successfully completed, the two
        endpoints use the established channel to exchange arbitrary
        NTPv4 packets as DTLS-protected Application Data.
      </t>
      <t>
        In addition to the requirements specified in <xref
        target="dtls-profile"/>, implementations MUST enforce the
        anti-replay mechanism specified in <xref target="RFC6347">
        Section 4.1.2.6 of RFC 6347</xref> (or an equivalent mechanism
        specified in a subsequent revision of DTLS). Servers wishing
        to enforce access control SHOULD either demand a client
        certificate or use a PSK-based handshake in order to establish
        the client's identity.
      </t>
      <t>
        The NTS-encapsulated NTPv4 protocol is the RECOMMENDED
        mechanism for cryptographically securing mode 1 (symmetric
        active), 2 (symmetric passive), and 6 (control) NTPv4 traffic.
        It is equally safe for mode 3/4 (client/server) traffic, but
        is NOT RECOMMENDED for this purpose because it scales poorly
        compared to using <xref target="nts-extensions-for-ntpv4">NTS
        Extensions for NTPv4</xref>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="The NTS Key Establishment protocol">
      <t>
        The NTS Key Establishment (NTS-KE) protocol is carried out by
        exchanging DTLS records using one of the two transports
        specified in <xref target="transport-mechanisms"/>. The two
        endpoints carry out a DTLS handshake in conformance with <xref
        target="dtls-profile"/>, with the client offering (via an
        <xref target="RFC7301">ALPN</xref> extension), and the server
        accepting, an application-layer protocol of
        &quot;ntske/1&quot;.  Immediately following a successful
        handshake, the client SHALL send a single request (as
        Application Data encapsulated in the DTLS-protected channel),
        then the server SHALL send a single response followed by a
        "Close notify" alert and then discard the channel state.
      </t>
      <t>
        The client's request and the server's response each SHALL
        consist of a sequence of records formatted according to <xref
        target="ntske-record"/>. The sequence SHALL be terminated by a
        &quot;End of Message&quot; record, which has a Record Type of
        zero and a zero-length body. Furthermore, requests and
        non-error responses each SHALL include exactly one NTS Next
        Protocol Negotiation record.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="ntske-record">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|C|         Record Type         |          Body Length          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                           Record Body                         .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        [[Ed. Note: this ad-hoc binary format should be fine as long
        as we continue to keep things very simple. However, if we
        think there's any reasonable probability of wanting to include
        more complex data structures, we should consider using some
        semi-structured data format such as JSON, Protocol Buffers, or
        (ugh) ASN.1]]
      </t>
      <t>
        The requirement that all NTS-KE messages be terminated by an
        End of Message record makes them self-delimiting. One DTLS
        record MAY, and typcially will, contain multiple NTS-KE
        records. NTS-KE records MAY be split across DTLS record
        boundaries. If, likely due to packet loss, an incomplete
        NTS-KE message is received, implementations MUST treat this an
        error, which clients SHOULD handle by restarting with a fresh
        DTLS handshake and trying again.
      </t>
      <t>
        The fields of an NTS-KE record are defined as follows:
        <list>
          <t>
            C (Critical Bit): Determines the disposition of
            unrecognized Record Types. Implementations which receive a
            record with an unrecognized Record Type MUST ignore the
            record if the Critical Bit is 0, and MUST treat it as an
            error if the Critical Bit is 1.
          </t>
          <t>
            Record Type: A 15-bit integer in network byte order (from
            most-to-least significant, its bits are record bits 7–1
            and then 15–8). The semantics of record types 0–5 are
            specified in this memo; additional type numbers SHALL be
            tracked through the IANA Network Time Security Key
            Establishment Record Types registry.
          </t>
          <t>
            Body Length: the length of the Record Body field, in
            octets, as a 16-bit integer in network byte order. Record
            bodies may have any representable length and need not be
            aligned to a word boundary.
          </t>
          <t>
            Record Body: the syntax and semantics of this field shall
            be determined by the Record Type.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <section title="NTS-KE record types">
        <t>The following NTS-KE Record Types are defined.</t>
        <section title="End of Message">
          <t>
            The End of Message record has a Record Type number of 0
            and an zero-length body. It MUST occur exactly once as the
            final record of every NTS-KE request and response. The
            Critical Bit MUST be set.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="NTS Next Protocol Negotiation">
          <t>
            The NTS Next Protocol Negotiation record has a record
            type of 1. It MUST occur exactly once in every NTS-KE
            request and response. Its body consists of a sequence of
            16-octet strings. Each 16-octet string represents a
            Protocol Name from the IANA Network Time Security
            Next Protocols registry. The Critical Bit MUST be
            set.
          </t>
          <t>
            The Protocol Names listed in the client's NTS Next
            Protocol Negotiation record denote those protocols which
            the client wishes to speak using the key material
            established through this NTS-KE session. The Protocol
            Names listed in the server's response MUST comprise a
            subset of those listed in the request, and denote those
            protocols which the server is willing and able to speak
            using the key material established through this NTS-KE
            session. The client MAY proceed with one or more of
            them. The request MUST list at least one protocol, but the
            response MAY be empty.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Error">
          <t>
            The Error record has a Record Type number of 2. Its body
            is exactly two octets long, consisting of an unsigned
            16-bit integer in network byte order, denoting an error
            code. The Critical Bit MUST be set.
          </t>
          <t>
            Clients MUST NOT include Error records in their request.
            If clients receive a server response which includes an
            Error record, they MUST discard any negotiated key
            material and MUST NOT proceed to the Next Protocol.
          </t>
          <t>
            The following error code are defined.
            <list>
              <t>
                Error code 0 means &quot;Unrecognized Critical
                Record&quot;. The server MUST respond with this error
                code if the request included a record which the server
                did not understand and which had its Critical Bit
                set. The client SHOULD NOT retry its request without
                modification.
              </t>
              <t>
                Error code 1 means &quot;Bad Request&quot;. The server
                MUST respond with this error if, upon the expiration
                of an implementation-defined timeout, it has not yet
                received a complete and syntactically well-formed
                request from the client. This error is likely to be
                the result of a dropped packet, so the client SHOULD
                start over with a new DTLS handshake and retry its
                request.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Warning">
          <t>
            The Warning record has a Record Type number of 3. Its body
            is exactly two octets long, consisting of an unsigned
            16-bit integer in network byte order, denoting a warning
            code. The Critical Bit MUST be set.
          </t>
          <t>
            Clients MUST NOT include Warning records in their request.
            If clients receive a server response which includes an
            Warning record, they MAY discard any negotiated key
            material and abort without proceeding to the Next
            Protocol. Unrecognized warning codes MUST be treated as
            errors.
          </t>
          <t>
            This memo defines no warning codes.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="AEAD Algorithm Negotiation">
          <t>
            The AEAD Algorithm Negotiation record has a Record Type
            number of 4. Its body consists of a sequence of unsigned
            16-bit integers in network byte order, denoting Numeric
            Identifiers from the IANA <xref target="RFC5116">AEAD
            registry</xref>. The Critical Bit MAY be set.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the NTS Next Protocol Negotiation record offers
            &quot;ntp/4&quot;,this record MUST be included exactly
            once. Other protocols MAY require it as well.
          </t>
          <t>
            When included in a request, this record denotes which AEAD
            algorithms the client is willing to use to secure the Next
            Protocol, in decreasing preference order. When included in
            a response, this record denotes which algorithm the server
            chooses to use, or is empty if the server supports none of
            the algorithms offered.. In requests, the list MUST
            include at least one algorithm. In responses, it MUST
            include at most one. Honoring the client's preference
            order is OPTIONAL: servers may select among any of the
            client's offered choices, even if they are able to support
            some other algorithm which the client prefers more.
          </t>
          <t>
            Server implementations of <xref
            target="nts-extensions-for-ntpv4">NTS extensions for
            NTPv4</xref> MUST support AEAD_AES_128_GCM (Numeric
            Identifier 1). That is, if the client includes
            AEAD_AES_128_GCM in its AEAD Algorithm Negotiation record,
            and the server accepts the &quot;ntp/4&quot; protocol in
            its NTS Next Protocol Negotiation record, then the
            server's AEAD Algorithm Negotation record MUST NOT be
            empty.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="New Cookie for NTPv4">
          <t>
            The New Cookie for NTPv4 record has a Record Type number
            of 5. The contents of its body SHALL be
            implementation-defined and clients MUST NOT attempt to
            interpret them. See [[TODO]] for a RECOMMENDED
            construction.
          </t>
          <t>
            Clients MUST NOT send records of this type. Servers MUST
            send at least one record of this type, and SHOULD send
            eight of them, if they accept &quot;ntp/4&quot; as a Next
            Protocol. The Critical Bit SHOULD NOT be set.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Key Extraction (generally)">
        <t>
          Following a successful run of the NTS-KE protocol, key
          material SHALL be extracted according to <xref
          target="RFC5705">RFC 5705</xref>. Inputs to the exporter
          function are to be constructed in a manner specific to the
          negotiated Next Protocol. However, all protocols which
          utilize NTS-KE MUST conform to the following two
          rules:
          <list>
            <t>
              The disambiguating label string MUST be
              &quot;EXPORTER-network-time-security/1&quot;.
            </t>
            <t>
              The per-association context value MUST be provided, and
              MUST begin with the 16-octet Protocol Name which was
              negotiated as a Next Protocol.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="NTS Extensions for NTPv4" anchor="nts-extensions-for-ntpv4">
      <section title="Key Extraction (for NTPv4)">
      <t>
        Following a successful run of the NTS-KE protocol wherein
        &quot;ntp/4&quot; is selected as a Next Protocol, two AEAD
        keys SHALL be extracted: a client-to-server (C2S) key and a
        server-to-client (S2C) key. These keys SHALL be computed
        according to <xref target="RFC5705">RFC 5705</xref>, using the
        following inputs.
        <list>
          <t>
            The disambiguating label string SHALL be
            &quot;EXPORTER-network-time-security/1&quot;.
          </t>
          <t>
            The per-association context value SHALL consist of the
            following 19 octets:
            <list>
              <t>
                The first 16 octets SHALL be (in hexadecimal):<vspace blankLines="1"/>
                &nbsp;&nbsp;6E&nbsp;74&nbsp;70&nbsp;2F&nbsp;34&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00&nbsp;00
              </t>
              <t>
                The next two octets SHALL be the Numeric Identifier of
                the negotiated AEAD Algorithm, in network byte order.
              </t>
              <t>
                The final octet SHALL be 0x00 for the C2S key and 0x01
                for the S2C key.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        Implementations wishing to derive additional keys for private
        or experimental use MUST NOT do so by extending the
        above-specified syntax for per-association context values.
        Instead, they SHOULD use their own disambiguating label
        string. Note that RFC 5705 provides that disambiguating label
        strings beginning with &quot;EXPERIMENTAL&quot; MAY be used
        without IANA registration.
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Packet structure overview">
        <t>
          In general, an NTS-protected NTPv4 packet consists of:
          <list>
            <t>
              The usual 48-octet NTP header, which is authenticated
              but not encrypted.
            </t>
            <t>
              Some extensions which are authenticated but not encrypted.
            </t>
            <t>
              An NTS extension which contains AEAD output (i.e., an
              authentication tag and possible ciphertext). The
              corresponding plaintext, if non-empty, consists of some
              extensions which benefit from both encryption and
              authentication.
            </t>
            <t>
              Possibly, some additional extensions which are neither
              encrypted nor authenticated. These are discarded by the
              receiver. [[Ed. Note: right now there's no good reason
              for the sender to include anything here, but eventually
              there might be. We've seen <xref
              target="RFC7821">Checksum Complement</xref> and LAST-EF
              as two examples of semantically-void extensions that are
              included to satsify constraints imposed lower on the
              protocol stack, and while there's no reason to use
              either of these on NTS-protected packets, I think we
              could see similar examples in the future. So, rejecting
              packets with unauthenticated extensions could cause
              interoperability problems, while accepting and
              processing those extensions would of course be a
              security risk. Thus, I think &quot;allow and
              discard&quot; is the correct policy.]]
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Always included among the authenticated or
          authenticated-and-encrypted extensions are a cookie
          extension and a unique-identifier extension. The purpose of
          the cookie extension is to enable the server to offload
          storage of session state onto the client. The purpose of the
          unique-identifier extension is to protect the client from
          replay attacks.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="The Unique Identifier extension">
        <t>
          The Unique Identifier extension has a Field Type of
          [[TBD]]. When the extension is included in a client packet
          (mode 3), its body SHALL consist of a string of octets
          generated uniformly at random. The string SHOULD be 32 octets
          long.  When the extension is included in a server packet (mode
          4), its body SHALL contain the same octet string as was
          provided in the client packet to which the server is
          responding. Its use in modes other than client/server is not
          defined.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Unique Identifier extension provides the client with a
          cryptographically strong means of detecting replayed
          packets. It may also be used standalone, without NTS, in
          which case it provides the client with a means of detecting
          spoofed packets from off-path attackers. Historically, NTP's
          origin timestamp field has played both these roles, but for
          cryptographic purposes this is suboptimal because it is only
          64 bits long and, depending on implementation details, most
          of those bits may be predictable. In contrast, the Unique
          Identifier extension enables a degree of unpredictability
          and collision-resistance more consistent with cryptographic
          best practice.
        </t>
        <t>
          [[TODO: consider using separate extension types for request
          and response, thus allowing for use in symmetric mode. But
          proper handling in the presence of dropped packets needs to
          be documented and involves a lot of subtlety.]]
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="The NTS Cookie extension">
        <t>
          The NTS Cookie extension has a Field Type of [[TBD]]. Its
          purpose is to carry information which enables the server to
          recompute keys and other session state without having to
          store any per-client state. The contents of its body SHALL
          be implementation-defined and clients MUST NOT attempt to
          interpret them. See [[TODO]] for a RECOMMENDED construction.
          The NTS Cookie extension MUST NOT be included in NTP packets
          whose mode is other than 3 (client) or 4 (server).
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="The NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions extension">
        <t>
          The NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions extension is
          the central cryptographic element of an NTS-protected NTP
          packet. Its Field Type is [[TBD]] and the format of its body
          SHALL be as follows:
          <list>
            <t>
              Nonce length: two octets in network byte order, giving
              the length of the Nonce field.
            </t>
            <t>
              Nonce: a nonce as required by the negotiated AEAD Algorithm.
            </t>
            <t>
              Ciphertext: the output of the negotiated AEAD
              Algorithm. The structure of this field is determined by
              the negotiated algorithm, but it typically contains an
              authentication tag in addition to the actual ciphertext.
            </t>
            <t>
              Padding: between 1 and 24 octets of padding, with every
              octet set to the number of padding octets included,
              e.g., &quot;01&quot;, &quot;02 02&quot;, or &quot;03 03
              03&quot;. The number of padding bytes should be chosen
              in order to comply with the <xref target="RFC7822">RFC
              7822</xref> requirement that (in the absence of a legacy
              MAC) extensions have a total length in octets (including
              the four octets for the type and length fields) which is
              at least 28 and divisible by 4. At least one octet of
              padding MUST be included, so that implementations can
              unambiguously delimit the end of the ciphertext from the
              start of the padding.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Ciphertext field SHALL be formed by providing the
          following inputs to the negotiated AEAD Algorithm:
          <list>
            <t>
              K: For packets sent from the client to the server, the
              C2S key SHALL be used. For packets sent from the server
              to the client, the S2C key SHALL be used.
            </t>
            <t>
              A: The associated data SHALL consist of the portion of
              the NTP packet beginning from the start of the NTP header
              and ending at the end of the last extension which precedes
              the NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions extension.
            </t>
            <t>
              P: The plaintext SHALL consist of all (if any)
              extensions to be encrypted.
            </t>
            <t>
              N: The nonce SHALL be formed however required by the
              negotiated AEAD Algorithm.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions extension
          MUST NOT be included in NTP packets whose mode is other than
          3 (client) or 4 (server).
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Protocol details">
        <t>
          A client sending an NTS-protected request SHALL include the
          following extensions:
          <list>
            <t>
              Exactly one Unique Identifier extension, which MUST be
              authenticated and MUST NOT be encrypted [[Ed. Note: so
              that if the server can't decrypt the request, it can
              still echo back the Unique Identifier in the NTS NAK it
              sends]].  MUST NOT duplicate those of any previous
              request.
            </t>
            <t>
              Exactly one NTS Cookie extension, which MUST be
              authenticated and MUST NOT be encrypted. The cookie MUST
              be one which the server previously provided the client;
              it may have been provided during the NTS-KE handshake or
              in response to a previous NTS-protected NTP request.  To
              protect client's privacy, the same cookie SHOULD NOT be
              included in multiple requests. If the client does not
              have any cookies that it has not already sent, it SHOULD
              re-run the NTS-KE protocol before continuing.
            </t>
            <t>
              Exactly one NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions
              extension, generated using an AEAD Algorithm and C2S key
              established through NTS-KE.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The client MAY include additional (non-NTS-related)
          extensions, which MAY appear prior to the NTS Authenticator
          and Encrypted Extensions extension (therefore authenticated
          but not encrypted), within it (therefore encrypted and
          authenticated), or after it (therefore neither encrypted nor
          authenticated). However, the server MUST discard any
          unauthenticated extensions and process the packet as though
          they were not present.
        </t>
        <t>
          Upon receiving an NTS-protected request, the server SHALL
          (through some implementation-defined mechanism) use the
          cookie to recover the AEAD Algorithm, C2S key, and S2C key
          associated with the request, and then use the C2S key to
          authenticate the packet and decrypt the ciphertext.  If the
          cookie is valid and authentication and decryption succeed,
          then the server SHALL include the following extensions in
          its response:
          <list>
            <t>
              Exactly one Unique Identifier extension, which MUST be
              authenticated, MUST NOT be encrypted, and whose contents
              SHALL echo those provided by the client.
            </t>
            <t>
              Exactly one NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions
              extension, generated using the AEAD algorithm and S2C
              key recovered from the cookie provided by the client.
            </t>
            <t>
              One or more NTS Cookie extensions, which MUST be
              authenticated and encrypted. Typically, multiple NTS
              Cookie extensions SHOULD be included; however, see <xref
              target="security-considerations"/> for discussion of
              exceptional cases wherein including multiple cookies
              could aggravate reflective DDoS attacks.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The server MAY include additional (non-NTS-related)
          extensions, which MAY appear prior to the NTS Authenticator
          and Encrypted Extensions extension (therefore authenticated
          but not encrypted), within it (therefore encrypted and
          authenticated), or after it (therefore neither encrypted nor
          authenticated). However, the client MUST discard any
          unauthenticated extensions and process the packet as though
          they were not present.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the server is unable to validate the cookie or
          authenticate the request, it SHOULD respond with a
          Kiss-o'-Death packet (see <xref target="RFC5905">RFC 5905,
          Section 7.4)</xref>) with kiss code &quot;NTSN&quot;
          (meaning &quot;NTS NAK&quot;). Such a response MUST
          include exactly one Unique Identifier extension whose
          contents SHALL echo those provided by the client.  It MUST
          NOT include any NTS Cookie or NTS Authenticator and
          Encrypted Extensions extension. [[Ed. Note: RFC 5905 already
          provides the kiss code &quot;CRYP&quot; meaning
          &quot;Cryptographic authentication or identification failed&quot;
          but I think this is meant to be Autokey-specific.]]
        </t>
        <t>
          Upon receiving an NTS-protected response, the client MUST
          verify that the Unique Identifier matches that of an
          outstanding request, and that the packet is authentic under
          the S2C key associated with that request. If either of these
          checks fails, the packet MUST be discarded without further
          processing.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Recommended format for NTS cookies" anchor="recommended-format-for-nts-cookies">
      <t>
        This section provides a RECOMMENDED way for servers to
        construct NTS cookies. Clients MUST NOT examine the cookie
        under the assumption that it is constructed according to this
        section.
      </t>
      <t>
        The role of cookies in NTS is closely analagous to that of
        session cookies in TLS. Accordingly, the thematic resemblance
        of this section to <xref target="RFC5077">RFC 5077</xref> is
        deliberate, and the reader should likewise take heed of its
        security considerations.
      </t>
      <t>
        Servers should randomily generate and store a master <xref
        target="AES">AES</xref> key `MEK` and a master <xref
        target="RFC4634">HMAC-SHA-256</xref> key `MAK`. Servers should
        additionally choose a non-secret, unique value `I` to identify
        the pair (MEK,MAK).
      </t>
      <t>
        Servers should periodically (e.g., once daily) generate a new
        triplet (I,MEK,MAK) and immediately switch to using these
        values for all newly-generated cookies. Immediately
        following each such key rotation, servers should securely
        erase any keys generated two or more rotation periods
        prior. Servers should continue to accept any cookie generated
        using keys that they have not yet erased, even if those keys are
        no longer current. Erasing old keys provides for forward
        secrecy, limiting the scope of what old information can be
        stolen if a master key is somehow compromised. Holding on to a
        limited number of old keys allows clients to seamlessly
        transition from one generation to the next without having to
        perform a new NTS-KE handshake.
      </t>
      <t>
        [[TODO: discuss key management considerations for load-balanced
        servers]]
      </t>
      <t>
        To form a cookie, servers should first form a plaintext `P`
        consisting of the following fields:
        <list>
          <t>The AEAD algorithm negotiated during NTS-KE</t>
          <t>The S2C key</t>
          <t>The C2S key</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Servers should then randomly generate an initialization vector
        `IV`, form ciphertext `C` by encrypting `P` in <xref
        target="CBC">CBC mode</xref> under key `MEK` with `IV` as the
        initialization vector, and then MAC the message `IV || C`
        (with || denoting concatenation) under key `MAK`, obtaining
        tag `T`.
      </t>
      <t>
        The cookie should consist of the tuple `(I,IV,C,T)`.
      </t>
      <t>
        [[TODO: explicitly specify how to verify and decrypt a cookie,
        not just how to form one]]
      </t>
      <t>
        Implementors may choose to substitute alternative algorithms
        in place of AES and SHA-256, but are discouraged from
        abandoning the combination of CBC and HMAC. CBC has the
        desirable property that the IV is random, is as wide as the
        cipher block, and that occasional collisions are unlikely to
        be fatal to security. In contrast, most IETF-standard AEAD
        schemes use a 96-bit nonce, and a single collision can break
        the security of everything ever authenticated under that key.
        AEAD nonces are generally expected only to be unique, not
        random, and 96 bits is too small for randomly-generated nonces
        to necessarily have a negligible risk of collision. However,
        use of sequential nonces in this context is a threat to
        privacy: a passive adversary could then count the responses
        emitted by the server and infer the nonces even though they
        are encrypted, then use this information to identify the
        client when it later returns the nonce in plaintext.
      </t>
      <t>
        A possible alternative approach, which would enable use of
        AEAD algorithms with short nonces without risk to security or
        privacy, is to use sequential nonces but avoid directly
        including them in the cookie; instead, protect them using a
        key-wrapping scheme such as <xref target="RFC3394">RFC
        3394</xref>. Another possibility is to use a <xref
        target="FPE">format-preserving encryption</xref> scheme to
        encrypt a counter, using its output as the nonce; to an
        adversary such nonces will be indistinguishable from random,
        yet have no risk of collision so long as the counter does not
        overflow.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
      <t>[[TODO. Outline follows.]]
      <list>
        <t>
          Cite <xref target="RFC7384">RFC 7384</xref> for general
          considerations.
        </t>
        <t>
          State security goals (authentication (defined in terms of
          agreement), client privacy) and threat model (active network
          adversary).
        </t>
        <t>
          Incorporate content from &quot;What Makes NTP Cryptographically Exceptional?&quot;
          of NTS design essay.
        </t>
        <t>
          Address strategies for management of AEAD nonces and stress importance
          of avoiding repetition.
        </t>
        <t>
          Give recommendations for validating X.509 certificates
          during the DTLS handshake. Discuss what to expect for the
          CN/SANs, and how to deal with verifying the validity period
          if correct time is not yet known.
        </t>
        <t>
          Caution that NTS will not prevent an adversary from skewing
          time by up to MAXDIST/2 and discuss why this limitation is
          fundamental.
        </t>
        <t>
          Possibly include informal security proofs.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations">
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate an entry in the Service Name and
        Transport Protocol Port Number Registry as follows:
        <list>
          <t>Service Name: nts</t>
          <t>Transport Protocol: udp</t>
          <t>Assignee: IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</t>
          <t>Contact: IETF Chair &lt;chair@ietf.org&gt;</t>
          <t>Description: Network Time Security</t>
          <t>Reference: [[this memo]]</t>
          <t>Port Number: selected by IANA from the user port range</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate the following two entries in the
        Application-Layer Protocol Negotation (ALPN) Protocol IDs
        registry:
        <list>
          <t>Protocol: Network Time Security Key Establishment, version 1</t>
          <t>
            Identification
            Sequence:<vspace/>&nbsp;&nbsp;0x6E&nbsp;0x74&nbsp;0x73&nbsp;0x6B&nbsp;0x65&nbsp;0x2F&nbsp;0x31&nbsp;("ntske/1")
          </t>
          <t>Reference: [[this memo]]</t>
        </list>
        <vspace/>
        <list>
          <t>Protocol: Network Time Protocol, version 4</t>
          <t>
            Identification
            Sequence:<vspace/>&nbsp;&nbsp;0x6E&nbsp;0x74&nbsp;0x70&nbsp;0x2F&nbsp;0x34&nbsp;("ntp/4")
          </t>
          <t>Reference: [[this memo]]</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate the following entry in the TLS
        Exporter Label Registry:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>DTLS-OK</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Note</ttcol>
        <c>EXPORTER-network-time-security/1</c>
        <c>Y</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
        <c/>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate the following entries in the registry
        of NTP Kiss-o'-Death codes:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Code</ttcol><ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>
        <c>DTLS</c><c>Packet conveys a DTLS record</c>
        <c>NTSN</c><c>NTS NAK</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to allocate the following entries in the
        NTP Extensions Field Types registry:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Field Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
        <c>[[TBD]]</c><c>DTLS Record</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
        <c>[[TBD]]</c><c>Unique Identifier</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
        <c>[[TBD]]</c><c>NTS Cookie</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
        <c>[[TBD]]</c><c>NTS Authenticator and Encrypted Extensions</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to create a new registry entitled
        &quot;Network Time Security Key Establishment Record Types&quot;.
        Entries SHALL have the following fields:
        <list>
          <t>
            Type Number (REQUIRED): An integer in the range 0–32767
            inclusive
          </t>
          <t>
            Description (REQUIRED): short text description of the
            purpose of the field
          </t>
          <t>
            Set Critical Bit (REQUIRED): One of &quot;MUST&quot;,
            &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;,  &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;,
            or &quot;MUST NOT&quot;
          </t>
          <t>
            Reference (REQUIRED): A reference to a document specifying
            the semantics of the record.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The policy for allocation of new entries in this registry SHALL vary
        by the Type Number, as follows:
        <list>
          <t>0–1023: Standards Action</t>
          <t>1024–16383: Specification Required</t>
          <t>16384–32767: Private and Experimental Use</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Applications for new entries SHALL specify the contents of the
        Description, Set Critical Bit and Reference fields and which
        of the above ranges the Type Number should be allocated
        from. Applicants MAY request a specific Type Number, and such
        requests MAY be granted at the registrar's discretion.
      </t>
      <t>
        The initial contents of this registry SHALL be as follows:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Field Number</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Critical</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
        
        <c>0</c>
        <c>End of message</c>
        <c>MUST</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>1</c>
        <c>NTS next protocol negotiation</c>
        <c>MUST</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
        
        <c>2</c>
        <c>Error</c>
        <c>MUST</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
        
        <c>3</c>
        <c>Warning</c>
        <c>MUST</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
        
        <c>4</c>
        <c>AEAD algorithm negotation</c>
        <c>MAY</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>5</c>
        <c>New cookie for NTPv4</c>
        <c>SHOULD NOT</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
        
        <c>16384–32767</c>
        <c>Reserved for Private &amp; Experimental Use</c>
        <c>MAY</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to create a new registry entitled
        &quot;Network Time Security Next Protocols&quot;.
        Entries SHALL have the following fields:
        <list>
          <t>
            Protocol Name (REQUIRED): a sequence of 16 octets. Shorter
            sequences SHALL implicitly be right-padded with null
            octets (0x00).
          </t>
          <t>
            Human-Readable Name (OPTIONAL): if the sequence of octets
            making up the protocol name intentionally represent a
            valid <xref target="RFC3629">UTF-8</xref> string, this
            field SHALL consist of that string.
          </t>
          <t>
            Reference (RECOMMENDED): a reference to a relevant
            specification document. If no relevant document exists, a
            point-of-contact for questions regarding the entry SHOULD
            be listed here in lieu.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Applications for new entries in this registry SHALL specify
        all desired fields, and SHALL be granted on a First Come,
        First Serve basis. Protocol Names beginning with 0x78 0x2D
        (&quot;x-&quot;) SHALL be reserved for Private or Experimental
        Use, and SHALL NOT be registered. The reserved entry
        &quot;ptp/2&quot; may be updated or released by a future
        Standards Action.
      </t>
      <t>
        The initial contents of this registry SHALL be as follows:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Protocol Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Human-Readable Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
        
        <c>&nbsp;&nbsp;0x6E&nbsp;0x74&nbsp;0x70&nbsp;0x2F&nbsp;0x34&nbsp;</c>
        <c>ntp/4</c>
        <c>[[this memo]]</c>

        <c>&nbsp;&nbsp;0x70&nbsp;0x74&nbsp;0x70&nbsp;0x2F&nbsp;0x32&nbsp;</c>
        <c>ptp/2</c>
        <c>Reserved by [[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        IANA is requested to create two new registries entitled
        &quot;Network Time Security Error Codes&quot; and
        &quot;Network Time Security Warning Codes&quot;. Entries in
        each SHALL have the following fields:
        <list>
          <t>Number (REQUIRED): a 16-bit unsigned integer</t>
          <t>Description (REQUIRED): a short text description of the condition.</t>
          <t>Reference (REQUIRED): a reference to a relevant specification document.</t>
        </list>
        The policy for allocation of new entries in these registries
        SHALL vary by their Number, as follows:
        <list>
          <t>0–1023: Standards Action</t>
          <t>1024–32767: Specification Required</t>
          <t>32768–65535: Private and Experimental Use</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The initial contents of the Network Time Security Error Codes Registry SHALL be as follows:
      </t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Number</ttcol><ttcol>Description</ttcol><ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
        <c>0</c><c>Unrecognized Critical Extension</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
        <c>1</c><c>Bad Request</c><c>[[this memo]]</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
        The Network Time Security Warning Codes Registry SHALL initially be empty.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3629;
      &rfc5116;
      &rfc5705;
      &rfc5746;
      &rfc5905;
      &rfc6347;
      &rfc7465;
      &rfc7507;
      &rfc7627;
      &rfc7301;
      &rfc7822;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="AES">
        <front>
          <title>
            Advanced Encryption Standard (AES)
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              National Institute of Standards and Technology
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2001"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS) Publication" value="197"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="CBC">
        <front>
          <title>
            Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation -
            Methods and Techniques
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              National Institute of Standards and Technology
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2001"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="NIST Special Publication" value="800-38A"/>  
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="FPE" target="https://eprint.iacr.org/2009/251.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>
            Format Preserving Encryption
          </title>
          <author fullname="Mihir Bellare" initials="M" surname="Bellare"/>
          <author fullname="Thomas Ristenpart" initials="T" surname="Ristenpart"/>
          <author fullname="Phillip Rogaway" initials="P" surname="Rogaway"/>
          <author fullname="Till Stegers" initials="T" surname="Stegers"/>
          <date year="2009"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="IEC.61588_2009"
                 target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=4839000">
        <front>
          <title>
            Precision clock synchronization protocol for networked
            measurement and control systems
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="2" month="February" year="2009"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              A protocol is provided in this standard that enables
              precise synchronization of clocks in measurement and
              control systems implemented with technologies such as
              network communication, local computing, and distributed
              objects. The protocol is applicable to systems
              communicating via packet networks. Heterogeneous systems
              are enabled that include clocks of various inherent
              precision, resolution, and stability to
              synchronize. System-wide synchronization accuracy and
              precision in the sub-microsecond range are supported
              with minimal network and local clock computing
              resources. Simple systems are installed and operated
              without requiring the management attention of users
              because the default behavior of the protocol allows for
              it.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="1588-2008(E)"/>
        <seriesInfo name="IEC" value="61588:2009(E)"/>        
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1109/IEEESTD.2009.4839002"/>
      </reference>
      &rfc3394;
      &rfc4634;
      &rfc5077;
      &rfc7384;
      &rfc7821;
    </references>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The author gratefully acknowledges the following contributors:
        Richard Barnes, Prof. Sharon Goldberg, Miroslav Lichvar,
        Aanchal Malhotra, Danny Mayer, Karen O'Donoghue, Eric
        K. Rescorla, Stephen Roettger, Rich Salz, Dieter Sibold, Brian
        Sniffen, Susan Sons, Harlan Stenn, and Kristof Teichel.
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
